Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's daf דף daf is Kuf
Yud Alef קיא, Kuf Yud Alef, 111, and we will, God willing,
begin the last and final perek פרק. perek. That's a little redundant.
Today okay, we pick up on Kuf Yud Alef amud bet קיא
עמוד ב, Kuf Yud Alef amud bet, though, and we pick up
by the two dots about 20 lines from the top. Ba'ei Rava
בעי רבא: Ba'ei Rava: Kohanim כהנים, Kohanim, so we're dealing again with
the whole case about gezel hager גזל הגר gezel hager and swearing,
and the Gemara גמרא Gemara had a whole question about that the
principal that is returned is required to allow for the bringing of
the asham אשם. asham. In a normal case when it wasn't a
gezel hager גזל הגר, gezel hager, it was a shevua שבועה shevua
and you bring an asham אשם, asham, then you need to give
the principal back, but the principal doesn't before you can get the
kapparah כפרה, kapparah, but the principal doesn't have a status, a korban
קרבן-like korban status. Here we have seen that it has a korban
קרבן-like korban status in the sense that it has to be returned
during the day, it has to be returned the full amount, it
can't—when the Kohanim כהנים Kohanim take it, they can't sort of combine
it with other moneys and divide it; each unit that was returned
has to be divided equally. So we're giving the money here a
whole status, a whole korban קרבן-like korban status. Okay, so now the
Gemara גמרא Gemara continues. If you tell the guy's like, listen, I
can't do it all today, I'll pay it in installments. But here
it's the Kohanim כהנים. Kohanim. So it's no, I mean, that's the
point, it's not just reimbursement. Ba'ei Rava בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava, so
Rava asks: Kohanim b'gezel hager, yorshim havu o mikablei matanos havu כהנים
בגזל הגר יורשין הוו או מקבלי מתנות הוו? Kohanim b'gezel hager, yorshim
havu o mikablei matanos havu? So now we've established that it's like
a korban קרבן, korban, but now we want to know what's somewhat
is the Kohanim's כהנים Kohanim's sort of monetary rights to it. Now
again, to repeat what we said the other day, which is that
because it has this korban קרבן-like—because korban it has this korban קרבן-like
korban status and only a korban קרבן-like korban status, if the guy
died—the guy who required the kapparah כפרה—the kapparah yorshim יורשין yorshim can
keep it. The Kohanim כהנים Kohanim don't have some monetary right to
it when it is not necessary as kapparah כפרה. kapparah. So if
the guy is dead and it's not necessary as kapparah כפרה, kapparah,
the Kohanim כהנים Kohanim can't claim it. Okay, that was what our
mishna משנה mishna said. But when, what if it is necessary as
kapparah כפרה kapparah and the guy's alive and he gives it to
the Kohanim כהנים? Kohanim? Do they get it as a gift? Or
do they get it as if they are the heirs of the
ger גר? ger? They become his appointed heirs. And again, I want
to reiterate that it's not that—only when it is doing the function
of kapparah כפרה. kapparah. They are not his assigned heirs from a
monetary perspective, but when it's doing the function of kapparah כפרה, kapparah,
are they there as receivers of it, like they would receive any
korban קרבן? korban? Or are they there as his appointed heirs? So
the Gemara גמרא Gemara says: L'mai nafka mina למאי נפקא מינה? L'mai
nafka mina? What difference does it make? K'gaun כגון, k'gaun, here's a
nafka mina נפקא מינה: nafka mina: she'gezel chametz she'avar alav ha'Pesach שגזל
חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח. she'gezel chametz she'avar alav ha'Pesach. Stole chametz חמץ
chametz from the ger גר ger that avar alav ha'Pesach עבר עליו
הפסח, avar alav ha'Pesach, and the guy swore about it. I'amrta yorshim
havu אי אמרת יורשין הוו, i'amrta yorshim havu, they're heirs, hinu hai
d'yorti
moris היינו האי דיורתיה מוריש. hinu hai d'yorti moris. So then they—what
you would give back would be the same thing you would give
back to the guy himself. So since to the guy himself you
would give back the chametz she'avar alav ha'Pesach חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח
chametz she'avar alav ha'Pesach even though it's worthless, you would give it
back to them. Okay, but that's if it's seen as give to
them when you are doing it as an act of kapparah כפרה—give
kapparah to them as if they are the ger גר. ger. Okay,
then you would give it to them even though it's worthless. V'i'amrta
mikablei matanos havu ואי אמרת מקבלי מתנות הוו, v'i'amrta mikablei matanos havu,
but if it's like some different track that the Torah תורה Torah
sets up, not give to them as if they were the ger
גר, ger, but now you must pay the Kohanim כהנים Kohanim what
you stole. So if that's true, havu lei matana k'rachmana d'neisivei lehu
הבו ליה מתנה דרחמנא דניתיבי להו. havu lei matana k'rachmana d'neisivei lehu.
So it says you should be noten נותן, noten, give, give them
something of value. V'halo lo yaiv lehu midi והלא לא יהיב להו
מידי, v'halo lo yaiv lehu midi, you're not giving them anything. Afra
b'alma hu עפרא בעלמא הוא. afra b'alma hu. It's just worthless. So
it's not seen as give to them as if they are the
ger גר ger and as if you're giving back to the ger
גר. ger. No, it would be a different track. It would be
give to them the value of what you stole. So if that's
true, you can't just give them this worthless chametz חמץ. chametz. What
about matnos kehuna מתנות כהונה? matnos kehuna? Well, we're going to get
to that actually, good that you mentioned that. So Rav Zeira ba'ei
hachi רב זירא בעי הכי. Rav Zeira ba'ei hachi. Rav Zeira רב
זירא Rav Zeira asks the following way: Afilu im timtzei lomar mikablei
matana havu אפילו אם תימצי לומר מקבלי מתנה הוו, afilu im timtzei
lomar mikablei מתנה הוו, he says no, that's not a nafka mina
נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Even if you say they're receiving a gift,
ha lo ibaya lan הא לא איבעיא לן. ha lo ibaya lan.
The question about chametz she'avar alav ha'Pesach חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח chametz
she'avar alav ha'Pesach is not our question. D'hi matana amar rachmana d'neisivei
lehu דהיא מתנה אמר רחמנא דניתיבי להו, d'hi matana amar rachmana d'neisivei
lehu, that is the gift that the Torah תורה Torah says you
give them, meaning the Torah תורה Torah says you give them what
you would have given the ger גר. ger. So if you would
have given the ger גר ger chametz she'avar alav ha'Pesach חמץ שעבר
עליו הפסח, chametz she'avar alav ha'Pesach, if that could have counted because
that's what you stole from him, that you can give them. So
it's not a question of what you give. You always give what
you would have given the ger גר. ger. The question is in
what capacity do they receive it? Okay, so then what would be
the nafka mina נפקא מינה? nafka mina? K'gaun she'naflu lo eser behemot
b'gezel hager כגון שנפלו לו עשר בהמות בגזל הגר. k'gaun she'naflu lo
eser behemot b'gezel hager. So basically, here's what happened. You, the Kohen
כהן, Kohen, there's some guy stole, I don't know, 10,000—you have to
steal a
lot because it's divided equally by the Kohanim כהנים Kohanim and you
have to have a small mishmar משמר—okay, mishmar but a guy stole
100,000 sheep and as gezel hager גזל הגר, gezel hager, and gave
it back to all the Kohanim כהנים, Kohanim, and each one of
them got 10 of them. Okay, so if you got 10 sheep
as a yerusha ירושה... yerusha... If you buy ten sheep in the
marketplace, you know, if you're given ten sheep as a gift, then
it, you don't have to give מעשר בהמה. maaser behema. So which
is it? Okay? מחייב להפריש מיניה מעשר או לא mechayev lehafrish minei
maaser o lo or not? ירושה ומלוה דאדם yerusha umilva de-adam or
are יורשים yorshim דאמר מר damar mar קנו בתפיסת הבית חייבים kanu
bitfisas habayis chayavim that if an estate buys, you know,
acquires sheep, wait a second, didn't the גר ger give the מעשר
בהמה maaser behema presumably?
No. What? I don't understand. No, why? In other words, if I,
you saying if I buy in a marketplace I don't have to
be מפריש מעשר בהמה. mafrish maaser behema. Right.
But these were in the גר'ס ger's possession and then someone stole
them. Right, why are we assuming the גר ger took מעשר בהמה?
maaser behema? Why would we assume he didn't? I don't know, meaning
like this whole thing could have been two days later, right? Okay,
but
it's a case that he did. Why do you have to make
it a case that he didn't? Or are you saying we know
that he didn't. Yeah. Oh, okay. So anyway, okay. So if somebody,
so if somebody inherited
sheep, okay, חייבין chayavin you have to be מפריש מעשר בהמה mafrish
maaser behema because the basic point is it is at the original
owner is מפריש מעשר בהמה mafrish maaser behema and therefore if you
inherit you're a continuation of the original owner and therefore you have
to be מפריש מעשר בהמה. mafrish maaser behema. או דילמא מקבלי מתנות
הוו o dilma mekablei matanos havay or maybe no, it's like you
are just getting a gift. דתנן הלוקח והניתן לו במתנה detnan halokeach
vehanitan lo bematana if somebody purchased sheep or gets it as a
gift פטור ממעשר בהמה, patur mimaaser behema, you're exempt. So when you
get this, are you getting this as heirs of the גר ger
and a continuation of the גר'ס ger's ownership and you have to
be מפריש מעשר בהמה mafrish maaser behema or are you getting this
as some new gift? So מה, ma, what's the הלכה? halacha? תא
שמע, ta shma, come and hear. So as Michael anticipated, let's look
at the list of what's considered מתנות כהונה. matnos kehuna. עשרים וארבע
מתנות כהונה ניתנו לאהרן ולבניו, esrim ve-arba matnos kehuna nitnu le-Aharon u-levanav,
24 gifts of כהונה kehuna were given to אהרן Aharon and his
sons. וכולן ניתנו בכלל ופרט וכלל, ve-chulan nitnu bichlal u-perat u-chlal, all
were given in כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-perat u-klal meaning the תורה
Torah introduces them it says, let's see רש"י Rashi quotes it, לכל
קדשי בני ישראל לך נתתים למשחה, lechol kodeshei bnei Yisrael lecha netatim
lemoshcha,
okay this is at the end of קרח, Korach, for all the
sanctities of בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael I have given them to you
for like for status, for greatness, okay and then it lists all
of them and then it says at the end בכל תרומת הקדשים,
bechol trumat hakodashim,
okay so it sort of lists them, it says a general statement,
it lists them and it says a general at the end. So
these 24 are included in that big general list. וברית מלח u-vrit
melach and it says at the end that this is like a
covenant of salt meaning an eternal covenant. כל המקימם kol himekayemam
anybody who fulfills them, presumably meaning the one who gives them, כאילו
מקיים כלל פרט וכלל ke-ilu mekayem klal perat u-klal it's like you
fulfilled all of them. וברית מלח u-vrit melach and this eternal covenant.
כל העובר עליהם kol haover aleihem and if you transgress giving any
one of them כאילו עובר על כלל פרט וכלל ke-ilu over al
klal perat u-klal it's like you had transgressed it in totality and
in particular. וברית מלח. u-vrit melach. ואלו הן ve-elu hein these are
they. עשר במקדש eser bamikdash ten that apply in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash וארבע בירושלים ve-arba bi-Yerushalayim four in ירושלים Yerushalayim that they
can only be eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim ועשר בגבולין ve-eser bagevulin and
ten in all places in ישראל. Yisrael. עשר במקדש eser bamikdash ten
in the מקדש. Mikdash. חטאת בהמה וחטאת העוף, chatas behema ve-chatas ha-of,
okay
so the animals meaning the sheep and the cows, the חטאת chatas
of an עוף of because again in these things they eat the
meat. ואשם ודאי ve-asham vaday an אשם asham that is brought for
a definite sin, one of the cases would be what we're talking
about, אשם גזילות asham gezelos is also מעילה me'ilah there's other אשמות.
ashamos.
אשם תלוי asham taluy which is brought for a doubtful sin, a
sin that if you knew about it for sure you'd bring a
חטאת, chatas, that's four. וזבחי שלמי ציבור ve-zivchei shalmei tzibur the communal
שלמים, shlamim,
you almost never have communal שלמים, shlamim, you have it by the
two lambs you bring on שבועות, Shavuos, they eat the meat, okay
but they only eat the meat normally a שלמים shlamim is eaten
all ירושלים Yerushalayim but a communal שלמים shlamim is קדשי קדשים kadshei
kodashim and eaten only in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, that's five.
ולוג שמן של מצורע ve-log shemen shel metzora the לוג log of
the oil of a מצורע metzora that's used in his קרבן korban
that he brings when he finishes his purification process, that's also only
eaten in the עזרה, azara, that's six. ומותר העומר u-mosar ha-omer what's
left over from the עומר omer which is a type of a
מנחה, mincha, so really it's true about all מנחות minchos but the
עומר'ס omer's a communal one so we're going to ושתי הלחם ולחם
הפנים, ve-shtei halechem ve-lechem hapanim, okay so we're going to list it
separately, so what's left over from the עומר מנחה omer mincha that's
seven, ושתי הלחם ve-shtei halechem they eat the two loaves that are
brought with on שבועות Shavuos that's
eight, ולחם הפנים ve-lechem hapanim and the bread that is sort of
that they eat once a week that's put on the table that's
nine, ושירי מנחות ve-shiyarei menachos and what's left over from any מנחה,
mincha, מנחה'ס mincha's קדשי קדשים, kadshei kodashim, that is ten.
וארבע בירושלים ve-arba bi-Yerushalayim four in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Those last four could
have been one. Yeah if you, yeah, but ten four and ten
is an easy way to remember.
Four in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. הבכור habechor the firstborn. הבכורה habechora which is
בכור bechor okay firstborn of animals, בכורים bikurim okay which is the
firstborn fruit this week's פרשה parsha firstborn first fruit ומהמורם מן התודה
v'hamuram min hatoda the part that they get from a תודה toda
קרבן korban which is the one of each of the sets of
the four sets of loaves plus they get you know the the
זרוע zeroah not the זרוע zeroah the what do you call it
the חזה chazeh and the שוק shok the breast and the thigh
okay which is what they get from all שלמים shlamim so this
set of תודה toda here includes שלמים shlamim okay so that's they
could have listed it separately but for whatever reason they want the
twenty-four number okay so that's three ואיל נזיר v'eil nazir and the
ram of a נזיר nazir which is also a type of a
you know שלמים shlamim so these are again why they call that
why they list that
separately ואיל נזיר v'eil nazir oh ומהמורם מן התודה ואיל נזיר u'mehamuram
min hatoda v'eil nazir excuse me thank you right we're combining that
תודה toda and איל נזיר eil nazir and all of שלמים shlamim
okay so they get their portion of the שלמים shlamim we're counting
that as one ועורות קדשים v'oros kodashim and the skin of the
קרבנות korbanot even of the קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim like if you
get an עולה olah or something so you can use the leather
okay but that you don't are not limited to using it in
the עזרה azarah okay so that is four interesting though go ahead
and use it for shoes and then walk outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim
with it apparently okay so
so those
that's the four and now we get what are the other ten
ועשרה בגבולין v'asara b'gvulin and ten that apply in all places hold
on just want to check רש״י Rashi one
thing yeah I wanted to check רש״י Rashi because it's not true
that you can't take the עור or outside of
ירושלים Yerushalayim that'd be very bizarre if you take a look at
רש״י Rashi four lines down in the wide lines רש״י Rashi says
like this beginning of the lines ומשום הכי קחשב להו בהדי הנך
דירושלים u'mishum hachi kachashiv lehu bahadi hanach d'Yerushalayim why do you count
the the skins of the קדשים kodashim in the things that are
in ירושלים Yerushalayim does that mean you can't if you make leather
out of you know the skin of the עולה olah you can't
go ahead and bring it out of ירושלים Yerushalayim he does says
no לאפוקי דאין נחשבין בהדי הנך דגבולין l'afokei d'ein nichshavin bahadi hanach
d'gvulin
to tell you that it's not included in things outside of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash means not that they can't be brought I
mean outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim but to tell you the following דהני
עורות לא מיתיהבי להו אלא בירושלים d'hanei oros lo mityahvi lehu ela
b'Yerushalayim
they're given to them in ירושלים Yerushalayim ובהדי דמקדש לא חשיב u'bahadi
d'mikdash lo chashiv
but it's not counted as things that are in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash אלא הני דאי נפקי חוץ לקלעים מיפסלי
ביוצא ela hanei d'ei nafki chutz l'kla'im mipsaly b'yotzai only things that
if you were to bring them out of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash they would become invalid so in a way רש״י Rashi is
saying here when it says the skin is given in ירושלים Yerushalayim
it's really capturing this weird middle status of the leather on the
one hand you give it as part of a קרבן korban so
it's brought in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash on the other hand
the כהן kohen can now use it and bring it anywhere okay
so you don't want to call say that it's something that applies
out in גבולין gvulin because it only comes to the כהן kohen
through a קרבן korban but you don't want to call it something
that's in the מקדש mikdash because it's not limited to being used
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash so saying ירושלים Yerushalayim is a
way of capturing the idea that it's given as a קרבן korban
in ירושלים Yerushalayim part of a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash but it's not limited to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
and in principle yes you can wear your leather shoes outside of
ירושלים Yerushalayim yes whereas we'll get to תרומה terumah חלה challah and
things like that and those can be given to any כהן kohen
anywhere exactly okay so those are the four that are that are
ירושלים Yerushalayim ועשרה בגבולין v'asara b'gvulin and ten that apply in the
you know in all places or all places in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael תרומה terumah right the first of
the grain ותרומת מעשר u'trumas ma'aser the tenth of the tenth that
a לוי Levi gets וחלה v'challah the separating of the חלה challah
וראשית הגז v'reishis hagez the first of the shearings והמתנות v'hamatanos and
the what we refer to as the זרוע לחיים וקיבה zeroah l'chayayim
v'keivah the parts of the animal that are given to a כהן
kohen when you שחט shacht an
animal ופדיון הבן u'pidyon haben the money given for פדיון הבן pidyon
haben ופדיון פטר חמור u'pidyon peter chamor and the sheep given when
you as a when you redeem a a donkey ושדה אחוזה u'sdei
achuza and the field of inheritance right when somebody sanctifies his field
of inheritance and he doesn't redeem it or somebody buys it it
goes to the כהנים kohanim we mentioned that the other day ושדה
חרמים u'sdei charamim similarly if somebody מחרים machrim another way of sanctifying
his field וגזל הגר v'gezel hager and money from the גר ger
that goes to the כהנים kohanim okay now so very good these
are listed in the thing now it is interesting that גזל הגר
gezel hager is mentioned as something בגבולין b'gvulin because you remember before
the גמרא Gemara said we couldn't give it בלילה balayla and you
couldn't give it לחצאין l'chatza'in right and all these things that make
it like a קרבן korban now it didn't explicitly say you couldn't
give it it didn't say you couldn't give it outside of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash but it consistently talks about giving it to
the משמר mishmar of כהנים kohanim right we had a little discussion
of could you give it to the משמר mishmar that's coming up
when it's not that משמר mishmar now where does the act of
giving it have to take place the fact that it says here
גבולין gvulin is strange so if you look at תוספות Tosafos look
at תוספות Tosafos you became חייב chayav outside right but like I
don't know a lot of קרבנות korbanot you Your sin outside ירושלים
*Yerushalayim* and the קרבן korban *korban* is still... look at תוספות Tosafot
*Tosfos*. גזל הגר gezel ha-ger. *gezel hager*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says תמה
*teimah*. אמאי חשיב גזל הגר gezel ha-ger: מעשרה בגבולין *amai chashiv gezel
hager measara bigvulin*. דהא דאמר רבא Rava, החזירו בלילה וחציו לא יצא
דאשם קריה רחמנא *deha de’amar Rava hechiziro balaylah vechetzyo lo yatza de’asham
karya Rachmana*. הכא נמי החזירו בגבולין לא יצא כדין אשם asham, *hacha
nami hechiziro bigvulin lo yatza kedin asham*. Right? He says where do
you give the גזל הגר gezel ha-ger. *gezel hager*? Right, can you
give it out if you give it outside the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash* outside of ירושלים *Yerushalayim* then why can't you give
it at night? To what degree is the act of giving the
גזל הגר gezel ha-ger? *gezel hager* like the act of bringing a
קרבן korban *korban*? Right, so it's a real good question why it's
kind of in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. רש״י *Rashi* says, look at רש״י *Rashi*
four lines from the bottom end of the line, גזל הגר gezel
ha-ger. נמי קרי ליה מתנות גבולין שנתנו לכהן המשמר חוץ לירושלים יצא
*gezel hager nami kari lei matnos gvulin shenisno lacohen hamishmar chutz l'Yerushalayim
yatza*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says, yeah you could give it. Okay, but
רש״י *Rashi* says you have to give it to the כהן kohen,
*kohen* of the משמר mishmar *mishmar* that's working. Okay? ואלו אשמו יעלה
לירושלים להקריב *v'elu ashamo ya'aleh l'Yerushalayim lehakriv*. So according to רש״י *Rashi*
he's trying to deal with תוספות׳ס *Tosfos's* problem, but he says, okay,
well, if you're a כהן *kohen* and your משמר mishmar *mishmar* is
working this week and you happen to have stayed home for whatever
reason, okay, I can give it to you outside of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*,
but it still counts as a קרבן korban, *korban* because it's your
group of כהנים kohanim, *kohanim* that are working this week, then you'd
have to inform them and split it with them I guess. Very
strange that we're treating the money to be קרבן korban *korban*-like in
all these ways, and we haven't really clarified where that act of
giving have to take place. One minute let's just finish what the
גמרא׳ס *Gemara's* doing with this and then I'll take your question. So
anyway we're back to our question: when they are receiving it are
they receiving it as a gift or they receiving it as if
they are the heirs of the גר *ger*? And the נפקא מינה
nafka mina *nafka mina* was מעשר בהמה *ma'aser beheima*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says וקר קרי ליה מתנה *ukar kari lei matana*. It
calls it a gift like everything else is a gift, like it
came to you new, not like it's some continuation of somebody else's
ownership. שמע מינה מקבלי מתנות הוו שמע מינה *shma mina mekablei מתנות
havu שמע מינה*. You see like all other things they are as
it were receiving gifts which makes sense because since again as we
said if the guy is dead you don't owe the money to
the גנב *ganav* the גזלן gazlan. *gazlan* is dead the kids don't
have to give the money to the כהנים kohanim *kohanim* they fundamentally
don't have monetary rights, they fundamentally it's only obligation
is that as an אשם asham? *asham* that is a type of
a קרבן korban *korban* that is for כפרה kapara *kapara*. So therefore
when they're receiving it they're not receiving as heirs of the גר
*ger*, they're receiving it just as they would receive anything that would
be given to the כהנים kohanim *kohanim*. Yes, Michael, you had a
question. Earlier you said when people are alive whether I stole from
a גר *ger* or a non-גר *ger* you don't have to worry
about this ירושלים *Yerushalayim* stuff, right? Right, this is only when the
כהנים kohanim *kohanim* are taking the place of the גר *ger*. That's
what I said at the beginning, that otherwise
giving back the money
is a prerequisite to bringing the אשם asham *asham* but it itself
is not considered like a קרבן korban *korban* א כפרה kapara. *a
kapara* and so on. It's a prerequisite. This fact that it has
a קרבן korban. *korban*-like status, you're giving it to the כהנים *kohanim*
is only by גזל הגר gezel ha-ger *gezel hager*. Yes, Charlie. Someone
that
lives, גבולין *gvulin* applies only within ארץ ישראל Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*, someone
apply everywhere? That is correct. גבולין *gvulin* sometimes
sort of not specific in terms of that. Yes. I do something
so basic I need to clarify. Like let's say I give you
five I give you five sheep on your 50th birthday as a
gift. Yeah. So then it becomes part of your general flock. I
don't take מעשר בהמה *ma'aser beheima* from it. מעשר בהמה *ma'aser beheima*
is only the animals that are born to my flock. They're not
just any, and that's why it's any of every ten new animals
that are born to my flock each year. So if I buy
them they're not animals that were born to my flock. So that's
really interesting, so then another way of conceptualizing ירושה *yerusha* is that
it's born into my flock. What is that? These are weather alerts?
Sorry, yes.
Everybody's phone. Yes, go ahead. Another way of conceptualizing a ירושה *yerusha*
is that it's born into my flock. Right, the ירושה *yerusha* is
a continuation of the previous ownership. So if none, no. Let me
be clear. If somebody's father had a hundred sheep and he was
יורש *yoresh* of them he does not give ten מעשר בהמה *ma'aser
beheima*. If somebody's father had ten sheep born to him that year
and then the father dies and then the person inherits it then
he gives. Only because he didn't take. Yeah, right, that's what I
was trying to clarify before, right. Things that a person gets in
ירושה *yerusha* are not like they were born to his flock. If
somebody gets them in ירושה *yerusha* he takes the place of the
person who died who bequeathed it to him. If that person's flock
was obligation was that would be his obligation. I don't know, I
don't have to do it. Correct. Yes. Okay, let's go oh well,
let's continue. All
right, so we say like this.
Now, just want to see something. Right,
okay, so now
continuing. נותן את הכסף לאנשי משמר mishmar *noson es hakesef l'anshei mishmar*.
So moving on in the משנה mishna *Mishnah*. The money was given
to the people of the משמר mishmar *mishmar* and then it says
and then the guy dies, the גזלן gazlan. *gazlan* died. Okay, so
remember if the גזלן gazlan *gazlan* died before anything was given over
the יורשים yorshim *yorshim* keep the money because the money is like
part of the כפרה kapara, *kapara* and if he's dead you no
longer do כפרה kapara, *kapara* for him after he's dead. Let's say
he gave and we just whole thing established that it was like
a מתנה *matana* the כהנים *kohanim* don't have to give it back.
any monetary rights to that money. So they gave the money though
and then the guy died. So the משנה Mishnah. says the יורשים
yorshim can't say, well, look, he's not getting his כפרה kapara. anyway,
give us back the rest of his money. Give us back his
money. They're not allowed to say that. So what can we infer
from this? Why, right? So I mean, why is that true? He
didn't get finished his כפרה. kapara, So אמר אביי, amar Abbaye, אביי
Abbaye says שמע מינה כסף מכפר מחצה. shma mina kesef mechaper mechtza.
You see from the משנה Mishnah. that the money achieves a partial
sense of atonement. Right? דלא מכפר de-lo mechaper if it did nothing
by itself, if it only achieved atonement together with the אשם, asham
so דלא מכפר הוה אמינא מהדר ליורשים. de-lo mechaper hava amina mehadar
le-yorshim.
So then the יורשים would have a right to say give it
back. Our father's dead,
the money was there as a כפרה, kapara. he's not going to
achieve the כפרה, kapara, give it back to us. Okay? So מאי
טעמא אדעתא דהכי לא יהב ליה. mai ta'ama adaata de-hachi lo yahav
lei.
They did not give it with that in mind. אלא, ella, what
the heck is going on today. Okay. אדעתא דהכי לא יהב ליה.
adaata de-hachi lo yahav lei. אלא, ella, לא יהב ליה. lo yahav
lei.
They didn't give it to him with the understanding... It wasn't just
סתם מתנה. stam matana. Here's a gift. No. They gave it in
the with the understanding that it should achieve atonement, it should function
as כפרה. kaparah, So if it didn't in the end function as
כפרה, kaparah. they should have a right to demand it back. So
therefore the fact that they can't demand it back shows that we
say that it did achieve some partial כפרה. kaparah That's אביי's Abbaye
argument. Okay, but now the גמרא Gemara, is going to challenge the
assumption of his argument. You, אביי, Abbaye, are assuming that if somebody
gives something without explicitly stipulating the conditions under which it's given, that
they can basically, you know, negate the gift or the sale based
on well I never intended that. Okay? So this is a really
important question. This is a question about how much an unarticulated assumption
can be used to, you know, negate, to void, a transaction. Okay,
big נפקא מינה's about this for like עגונה aguna questions. Okay, on
this condition I never would have agreed, etc. Okay. So let's take
a look. אלא מעתה, ella me-ata, says the גמרא, Gemara okay, we
understand where you're coming from אביי, Abbaye, that for you it's important
to say that it was a partial כפרה, kaparah or they would
have a right, but let's challenge that question. Can you really say,
hey, I didn't expect this, give it back to me? אלא מעתה,
ella me-ata, if that's true, חטאת שמתו בעליה, chatas she-mesu be'aleha,
let's say I sanctify an animal... somebody, ראובן Reuven sanctifies an animal
as a חטאת, chatas, and then he dies. So what's the הלכה?
halacha? The חטאת chatas has to be let to die because the
owner has died. So why don't you say, oh no, he never
sanctified it assuming he would die? So תיפוק לחולין, teipuk le-chulin, let
it no longer... let it become desanctified. דאדעתא דהכי לא אפרשה. de-adaata
de-hachi lo afrisha. He never separated it off as a קרבן korban
thinking he would die. If that had... if that thing had happened
in the future that he hadn't anticipated now, if we're going to
let the future thing say oh had I been thinking of that
future event I never if I would have known it would have
happened I wouldn't have done it. So if that's true, let it
not be a חטאת. chatas. So the גמרא Gemara says,
in theory you're right, but חטאת שמתו בעליה הלכתא גמירי לה, chatas
she-mesu be'aleha hilchisa gemiri la, that's a הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha le-Moshe
mi-Sinai, דלמיתה אזלא, de-lemisa azla, that it dies. So in theory it's
a good argument, you know, it really probably shouldn't be קדוש, kadosh,
but that's just that's the הלכה halacha there. אלא מעתה, ella me-ata,
okay, let's go on again. If you're going to say that had
something happened in the future I never would have given... I never
would have done this and we should use that to redefine what
I did, אשם שמתו בעליו ליפוק לחולין, asham she-mesu be'alov leipuk le-chulin,
how about an אשם? asham There the הלכה halacha is that if
the owner's died you wait to redeem it and you transfer the
money out onto... onto like onto an עולה. ola. Why why not
there, let's say that it's not
sanctified? דאדעתא דהכי לא אפרשה. de-adaata de-hachi lo afrisha. He didn't separate
it thinking he was going to die. Or had he known he
was going to die he wouldn't have separated it. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, אשם נמי הלכתא גמירי לה. asham nami hilchisa gemiri
la. No, it's also a הלכה, halacha, a tradition. Okay. שכל שבחטאת
מתה, she-kol she-be-chatas mesa, anything that had it been a חטאת chatas
you'd let die, באשם רועה, be-asham ro'eh, by an אשם asham, it
grazes until it gets a blemish. So in principle you're right, they
shouldn't be קדוש, kadosh, but that's the הלכה. halacha. אלא
מעתה, ella me-ata, okay, let's deal another case where you can't say
it's a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. יבמה שנפלה לפני מוכה
שחין. yevama she-nafla lifnei mukeh shechin. A woman's husband dies and the
brother turns out to be a degenerate... actually here it doesn't say
degenerate. Here it says the woman's brother turns out to be somebody
afflicted with a... you know, whatever, what's it, a boils and puss
and whatever, a disgusting, you know, repulsive person. So תיפוק בלא חליצה.
teipuk le-lo chalitza. She should be able to, you know, to to
just not... to walk away, it shouldn't even require חליצה, chalitza, especially
if it's hard to get חליצה. chalitza. דאדעתא דהכי לא קידשה עצמה.
de-adaata de-hachi lo kidshta atzma.
She never would have agreed to marry her husband had she known
that the what do you call it, you know, had she known
that the husband would die and that the brother would turn out
to be this disgusting guy. Had she been able to anticipate all
this future which was completely unforeseen at the time, okay, she never
would have done it. So if you can say that we can
use that to retroactively redefine her דעת... da'at... and she didn't... I
mean, what does it mean? Like let's say she didn't know, then
they'll be okay? I mean, okay, maybe... okay, maybe, but she well
she didn't know the husband would die and who would die first.
So had we say that we can use that to... If you
say if you had looked into the future you would have seen
this, you never would have done it now. If that's a good
basis, so then she should not be now considered married to her
husband and not require חליצה chalitzah or יבום. yibum. Do you understand
why this could be very relevant for discussions of עגונה? agunah? Okay.
הלאי בני הלאי, hala'i bnei hala'i,
had I known that my husband would have withheld the גט, get,
I never would have, you know, agreed to marry him in the
first place. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, התם אנן סהדי דמינח
ניחא לה בכל דהוא. hasam anan sahadei d'minach nicha lah b'chol d'hu.
No,
there we know that even had she been able to anticipate that,
she still would have wanted to have been married to her husband
now for the time being, even knowing what was,
even knowing what might come up in the future, as רש"י Rashi
says. That's like ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says, דאמר ריש לקיש, d'amar Reish Lakish, טב למיתב טן דו מלמיתב
ארמלו. tav le-meitav tan du mi-le-meitav armelu. It is better to sit
two together than to sit as a widow or to sit alone.
So this is the גמרא's Gemara assumption, right, that women are willing,
like to agree to be married under, you know, it's a much
higher threshold needed to assume that a woman wouldn't have wanted to
be married, which as you could imagine creates a lot of challenges
again in this sort of עגונה agunah sphere. But here the גמרא
Gemara says that at least without these exceptions, the גמרא Gemara seems
to say in principle you could say, had I been able to
anticipate this would have happened in the future, I never would have
bought it. So the question is like, really? Like what's the extent
of that? Like why don't I say for Michael, I bought Michael's
nice iPhone, there I'm always buying the iPhone, and then it slips
out of my hand and it breaks or whatever and I say,
had I known that would have happened, I never would have bought
it. Now maybe that was my fault, okay, but let's say I
buy, you know, I buy a car from Michael and I get
a Samsung. I buy a Samsung, right, and then it blows up
and it turns out it was a defect that wasn't his fault,
wasn't my fault, had I known about it. Or I buy a
car from Michael and I get it checked out, Michael didn't deceive
me or anything like that, but then, you know, even if you
get it checked out, sometimes a month later, you know, the carburetor
blows. Oh, had I known that I never would have bought it.
So no sale is ever final. So it's crazy. So תוספות Tosafot
says, that's why all these cases, תוספות Tosafot says, are primarily
unilateral. Now קרבן korban is clearly unilateral. There's not another side that
has, because normally we say דברים שבלב אינם דברים, dvarim she-belev einam
dvarim, if it's not an articulated condition, doesn't matter what's in my
head. So the קדשים kodashim cases are clearly unilateral. How about the
קידושין kiddushin case? So תוספות Tosafot says, ah, the קידושין kiddushin case
is unilateral in the sense that the husband's already dead. So to
sort of say in this condition I never would have married my
husband, he's no longer a side in the conversation because he's dead.
You're only getting out of the marriage to the husband in order
to free you from the brother-in-law, right? So in that type of
a case, the ability to claim I never would have agreed under
these circumstances when you're not really hurting or impacting the other side
of the transaction—there is no other side in this case because the
husband is dead—there you might have more latitude, okay. And in the
case of the כהנים, presumably the giving of the gift, if you're
just a passive receiver of a gift that is seen and you're
not exchanging it for anything, that seems as more unilateral. So this
raises the idea that דברים שבלב אינם דברים, dvarim she-belev einam dvarim,
what you're thinking isn't relevant to what you theoretically would have been
thinking. Here you're not even thinking it; it's only had I been
able to think about the possibility, what would I have thought now
anyway, תוספות Tosafot is only considering that here in things that are
more unilateral, which again means it has much less use in thinking
about קידושין kiddushin cases. The final thing I want to say about
this, I mean this is a huge ideas that are set in
these three lines, but the final thing I want to say about
this is is that I don't understand the גמרא's Gemara comparison to
אביי's Abaye case at all. All these cases you had fundamentally a
transaction and then you had some external consideration, sanctifying something as a
חטאת. chatat. Oh, had he known he would have died. Marrying this
guy, had he known the husband would have died, etcetera. But the
fundamental act was an act of קידושין, kiddushin, of being מקדיש makdish
something or of קידושין. kiddushin. The fundamental act was exactly what it
was defined to be, right? In this case, okay, when the guy
gives this thing as a כפרה, kapara he's not giving it as
a gift, he's giving it as a קרבן, korban he's giving it
as a כפרה. kapara Okay, so it wasn't a gift. So it
wasn't a gift, so why do the כהנים say we have right
to it? You don't have right to it. It was given to
you as a כפרה kapara. and it no longer has function, it
didn't, and assuming that it doesn't function until the אשם asham, is
brought, right, that's אביי's Abaye argument, and the אשם asham, is not
being brought because the guy is dead, then it stops being what
it was given to you as. It's not some external reason to
negate it. It was only given in the context of a כפרה
kapara and it never and again—it's like I don't know, I gave
a down payment, okay, and then in the end I didn't go
through with the transaction. I get my down payment back. You don't
say, oh well, that's trying to use your דעת da'at had you
known. No, it was given in the context of a down payment.
So if the transaction didn't complete, why don't I get it back?
I don't really understand the parallel the גמרא Gemara is making from
אביי's Abaye case to these cases. What did you want to say,
Jenna? I mean, I guess it just depends on how connected it
is with the אשם, asham right? But like, is it that it's
the first step in it or is it a separate thing that
you're giving? So that's what אביי *Abaye* says. אביי *Abaye* says I'm
going to prove that it does something by itself. Because if it
didn't do something by itself, you'd be entitled to get it back.
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, why would you be entitled to
get it back? That's just some דעת *Da'as* that you have unarticulated.
No, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is arguing. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
that we don't buy your argument, meaning the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s pushback
is saying, even if it doesn't do something by itself, it's not
so clear that your דעת *Da'as*, unarticulated דעת *Da'as*, should allow you
to reclaim it. That was the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s challenge of אביי
*Abaye*. And my point is this is not just some unarticulated דעת
*Da'as*. This is the whole context in which it's being given. What
you basically said back to me was exactly אביי *Abaye*'s point. But
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s pushing back against אביי *Abaye*. גמרא *Gemara* says,
maybe not, maybe they're entitled to it even if it didn't achieve
anything because it was just they gave him a gift. They can't
ask for it back, or he can't ask for it back. And
the גמרא *Gemara* says, why not? It wasn't given as a gift.
It was given as a כפרה kapara. *Kaparah*. So I don't exactly
get the גמרא *Gemara*'s pushback, but anyway, very important גמרא *Gemara* in
terms of this question about to what degree might future issues, like
and you could say אדעתא דהכי לא *A'da'ata de-hachi lo* and that
condition I never would have and so on.
Does that logic follow all of the נדרים *Nedarim*?
I mean, there is an issue about דעת *Da'as*. נדרים *Nedarim* is
much more sort of unilateral and so on. But you have there
that concept being centrally motivated. One place that this comes up, by
the way, is a case where and where you don't can't say
like טב למיטב טן דו *Tav le-meitav tan du*, is that a
guy turns out to be abusive and that becomes like clear like
right after, very soon after the marriage. So if it's,
so anyway, there are times where you could sort of say, had
I known so and so on, I never would have, but anyway,
but there could also be a case where something is being hidden
at the time of the transaction itself. All right, anyway, let's continue.
נתן את הכסף ליהויריב *Nasan es hakesef le-Yehoyariv*. So now the משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah* goes on and says, if the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* was
given, יהויריב *Yehoyariv* is the first משמר mishmar *Mishmar*, and then it
was the אשם asham *Asham* was given to the משמר *Mishmar* that
follows, that's fine. The כסף *Kesef* has to be given first. But
if the order was reversed, you were not יוצא *Yotze* the אשם
asham *Asham* if it was offered before the money was given. So,
תנו רבנן tana rabbanan: *Tanu Rabbanan*, our rabbis taught. נתן אשם asham
ליהויריב והכסף לידעיה *Nasan asham le-Yehoyariv vehakesef le-Yedaya*. So that's a
case that the אשם asham? *Asham* was given first and then the
money was given to the next משמר *Mishmar*. יחזיר כסף אצל אשם
asham *Yachzir kesef etzel asham*. So the כסף *Kesef* goes back to
the אשם asham *Asham*. Now, of course, that means that's funny. The
כסף *Kesef* was given to the following משמר *Mishmar*, but obviously the
scenario must be it's still the first משמר *Mishmar*'s week. You gave
it in advance, because how are you going to get the כסף
*Kesef* back if it's already the next week? That's somebody, I'm remembering
that the New York Times many years ago ran an article about
how bad the signage is in New York. And somebody wrote a
letter and said the best or the worst example that they remember
is that they were once driving like down the highway and they
saw a sign that said: Exit out, use exit 3 miles back.
So anyway, so if it's already the next week, you
can't give the כסף *Kesef* back to the previous week, right? They've
already done, they've left. All right, anyway, so presumably you gave the
כסף *Kesef* in advance to the next, to the next משמר *Mishmar*,
and then it says: No, then give it back to the current
משמר *Mishmar*, because the כסף *Kesef* has to come first. יחזיר כסף
אצל אשם asham, *Yachzir kesef etzel asham*, דברי רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
*Divrei Rabbi Yehudah*. That's what רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehudah* said.
וחכמים אומרים *Vachachamim omrim*, the חכמים *Chachamim* say: יחזיר אשם asham אצל
כסף *Yachzir asham etzel kesef*. No, the אשם asham *Asham* goes to
the next משמר *Mishmar*. So presumably the אשם asham *Asham* has not
been slaughtered yet. Obviously then it would be פסול psul *Pasul*. היכי
דמי *Heichi dami*? What's the case? אילימא דיהב אשם asham, ליהויריב במשמרתו
דיהויריב *Ileima de-yav asham le-Yehoyariv bemishmarto de-Yehoyariv*, you gave the אשם asham
*Asham* to משמר *Mishmar* number one when it was its week, במשמרתו
דיהויריב *bemishmarto de-Yehoyariv*, והכסף לידעיה במשמרתו דידעיה *vehakesef le-Yedaya bemishmarto de-Yedaya*, and
you gave the כסף *Kesef* to משמר *Mishmar* number two in its
week, במשמרתו דידעיה *bemishmarto de-Yedaya*. זה זכה בשלו וזה זכה בשלו *Zeh
zach bishlo vezeh zach bishlo*. It's too late. Each one gets its
own. Which doesn't mean that the אשם asham. *Asham* was good, but
it basically means that you understand the חכמים *Chachamim* saying that if
they haven't been מקריב makriv *makriv* yet the אשם asham. *Asham*, they
left their week without being מקריב makriv *makriv* the אשם asham. *Asham*,
let them give the אשם asham *Asham* to number two. But you
don't understand how רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehudah* would say, if
number one's week is over, give the כסף *Kesef* back to guys
number one, they're already out of here. You know, how what sense
does that make? So אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, so רבא *Rava* said,
הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai askinan, *hacha be-mai askinan*, what are we
talking about? דיהב אשם asham ליהויריב במשמרתו דיהויריב *de-yav asham le-Yehoyariv bemishmarto
de-Yehoyariv*. It's week number one. You gave the אשם asham *Asham* to
group number one. והכסף לידעיה במשמרתו דיהויריב *vehakesef le-Yedaya bemishmarto de-Yehoyariv*. And
you gave the כסף *Kesef* to ידעיה *Yedaya* a week in advance
while it was still week number one. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda סבר
*Rabbi Yehudah savar*, now, so what do you do now? So you
have to have the כסף *Kesef* first, but the כסף *Kesef* was
already given to group number two. רבי יהודה סבר *Rabbi Yehudah savar*,
כיון דלאו משמרת דידעיה היא *keivan delav mishmeres de-Yedaya hi*, since it
was not group number two's week, לידעיה קנסינן לה *le-Yedaya kensinan lah*,
ידעיה *Yedaya* is the one that has to make the sacrifice, excuse
the pun, they have to give up what they've got. They have
to give their כסף *Kesef* back to group number one. הלכך Hilkach
יחזיר כסף אצל אשם asham. *Hilkach yachzir kesef etzel asham*. Give the
כסף *Kesef* to group number one. Group number one will take the
כסף *Kesef* and then they'll be able to bring the אשם asham
*Asham*. ורבנן סברי *Verabbanan savrei*, and the רבנן Rabanan, *Rabbanan* hold, שלא
כדין עבד בני יהויריב *shelo kedin avad benei Yehoyariv*. No,
group number one did the wrong thing because why? דקבילו אשם asham
בקמי כסף *dikiblu asham bikmi kesef*, even though it was their week...
week, they're not supposed to agree to accept the sacrifice before they've
been given the money. הלכך
therefore because they did the wrong thing by accepting a sacrifice without
the money coming first. הלכך לדידהו קנסינן להו ledidehu kansinan lehu we
fine them ויחזיר אשם אצל כסף veyachzir asham etzel kesef where they're
told don't bring the אשם, asham. give it to group number two
and let group number two bring it next week. Okay, תניא Tanya
we taught a ברייתא. Braita. אמר רבי Amar Rebbi Rebbi said, לדברי
רבי יהודה ledivrei Rebbi Yehuda according to רבי יהודה that says group
number two has to give the money back to group number one
and if it's still group number one's week, אם קדמו בני יהויריב
והקריבו את האשם im kidmu bnei Yehoyariv vehikrivu et ha'asham if group
number one jumped ahead and brought the אשם, asham. יחזור ויביא אשם
אחר yachzor veyavi asham acher then the guy has to bring another
אשם asham, because it was an אשם asham brought before the money
was given. ויקריבו בני ידעיה veyikrivu bnei Yedaya
and group number two will bring the אשם asham because the money
was given to group number two.
Yeah, well, that's a good point, presumably the owner, I mean that
gets to a whole general question. What owner? The
גזלן. gazlan Yeah, the גזלן. gazlan, Yeah, the גזלן gazlan gets to
a whole general problem that when כהנים make mistakes it's the owners
who pay. Okay, but anyway, that's a whole separate question. Yeah. וזכו
הללו במה שבידם. vezachu halalu bema shebeyadam. Okay, and they, group number
one, since the קרבן korban was no good, so the קרבן korban.
is now going to be brought by group number two, but group
number one at least gets to keep the אשם asham. that they
already brought. So what does that mean? The גמרא says, אמלי למאי
חזי אשם פסול הוא. amlei lemai chazi asham pasul hu. What do
you mean group number one keeps the אשם? asham It's invalid! So
it was brought before the money. So אמר רבא לעורו. amar Rava
le'oro. Okay, they can't eat the meat, but they can eat the
skin, they can use the leather. All right, so presumably that sounds
like a קרבן פסול, korban pasul, you can still use the leather,
and תוספות Tosafot challenges that because elsewhere it seems like you can't
use the leather of a קרבן פסול. korban pasul. And תוספות Tosafot
really leaves it as a question. I would suggest, you know, it's
a funny type of a פסול psul here. A normal פסול psul
is the blood was spilled, the animal had a blemish, you know,
it was פיגול. pigul. Okay, there's an intrinsic problem in the animal
itself. Here the animal is 100% כשר, kosher, it's just that it
didn't achieve כפרה kapara. because it preceded the money. Okay, so that
type of a פסול psul that is a type of a פסול
דחוץ לגופו, psul dechutz legufo, intrinsically it's a קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim
but it did not achieve כפרה for the owners, right? There, you
know what it would be like? It would be like let's say
somebody was שוחט shochet a קרבן שלא לשמו. korban shelo lishmo. Okay,
if you bring a קרבן שלא לשמו korban shelo lishmo the קרבן
korban. is כשר, kosher, but the בעלים be'alim don't get כפרה. Okay,
so there, you know, you could go ahead and benefit with the
leather. The point is it's not totally like that because if I
שחט shacht a קרבן שלא לשמו korban shelo lishmo I still get
to eat the meat. Okay, here it seems to say you don't
get to eat the meat, the only thing they get is the
leather. So it's this weird type of a middle status where it's
not an intrinsic פסול pasul so they still get to eat the
leather, but it's not a completely, you know, sort of external problem
and they can't eat the meat of the קרבן. korban. So it's
a strange issue that תוספות asks about. Yeah. Is there, would you
say, is there a religious idea behind the fact that the כפרה
depends upon the giving of the money first, you have to... Yeah,
we mentioned that, it's like the classic, exactly, it's like the classic
thing that we say in מסכת יומא, Masechet Yoma, you know, you
can't ask forgiveness from God before you're מרצה את חבירו. meratzeh et
chaveiro. It's so dead in this...
I know, it's funny that the גמרא never said that explicitly, but
right, don't start bringing your קרבן korban. to God until you've made
restitution. Right. Okay, so the גמרא says like this. Okay. לעורו. le'oro.
תניא Tanya we taught another ברייתא. Braita. אמר רבי Amar Rebbi Rebbi
said, לדברי רבי יהודה ledivrei Rebbi Yehuda according to רבי יהודה that
says the money goes back to group number one,
אם קיים אשם יחזיר אשם אצל כסף im kayam asham yachzir asham
etzel kesef if the אשם asham is around, then it follows the
money. Follow the money. So the גמרא says one minute, that's not,
that's the רבנן, that's not רבי יהודה. והא רבי יהודה יחזיר כסף
אצל אשם אית ליה. veha Rebbi Yehuda yachzir kesef etzel asham it
lei. רבי יהודה is the one that says the money goes to
where the אשם asham is! So the גמרא says הכא במאי עסקינן,
Hacha bemai askinan, no, here's the case. כגון דנפק משמרתה דיהויריב. kegon
denafak mishmartah deYehoyariv. It was
group number one had the אשם, asham group number two had the
money, and group number one never brought the אשם asham and their
week is over. Okay, so they still have this little animal with
them, what are they going to do with it? ולא תבעו velo
tavu
and they never said to group number two give us the money,
we demand, we have rights to the money. דקא משמע לן deka
mashma lan so this is teaching us דכולי אחולי גבייהו dechulei acholi
gabayihu
they essentially are מוחל mochel their rights to the money and in
that case their week is over and they never asked for the
money from group number two, they give the animal, they give the
אשם asham over to group number two for them to be מקריב
it. Now, and I have a couple of questions about this. Number
one, even if they did demand the money, okay, if group number
two never handed it over, okay, I mean, you know, then what
are you supposed to do then? Wait a year till it's group
number one's turn again to bring it? Like, you know, the קרבן
korban, will probably be פסול anyway because, you know, קרבנות korbanot have
an expiration, I mean in the sense that the animals can't be,
have to be a certain age. I'd like... well, actually it's not
true though, because it's twenty-four משמרות, mishmarot, so you'll only have to
wait a half year. But even so, the animal still might be
too old. So like I don't get it, even if they did
demand it, I'm not sure what. but the other question I've got
is a general issue, which is if it was my week to
bring a קרבן korban and we didn't bring this animal, like you
know it was a big backup, we had 20 animals that were
given to us or 2,000 animals, some we didn't bring, presumably the
normal standard operating procedure is you hand it over to the next
משמר and they bring it, you know, during their week, right? So
this is just like, so wouldn't this be the normal thing? We
had an אשם asham to bring, we didn't have a chance to
bring it, you give it over to the next group, you know?
It's so it is funny that it uses this phrase of like
they were מוחל mochel their rights to the money. Like it's just
they didn't bring the קרבן korban. during their week. So I don't
know, yes.
Maybe it means that maybe maybe the הוה אמינא hava amina is,
oh here could be the הוה אמינא. hava amina. The הוה אמינא
hava amina is that group number two should give the money to
group number one and then group number two would bring the קרבן.
korban Ah that would be the thing. If group number one had
the rights to the money, then maybe they could keep their rights
to the money even as group number two is going to bring
the קרבן. korban Yeah. So I just sort of
suggested, you see 100 animals, I mean to me they all look
alike. Right. Have some system of markers like this one's birthday is
next week?
Yeah that's a good question. I don't know. I don't know. I
thought you were going to say a system of markers so they
knew which is a חטאת, chatas, which is an עולה. olah. That
too. Right. All these things. Yeah I don't know. That's a good
question. They have to, you know, they gotta get one of those
like scanners in there and they tag them.
Exactly. That would make it much better. Alright. Good, very good. Moving
on.
Okay. Alright, moving on. Okay.
תניא, Tanya, we learned in a בריתא. braita. אמר רבי, Amar Rebbi,
לדברי רבי יהודה Ledivrei Rabbi Yehuda according to Rabbi Yehuda who says
the money goes to the
אשם, asham אם קיים אשם יחזיר כספו אצל אשם, Im kayam asham
yachzir kaspo etzel asham, if the אשם asham is still around, the
money goes back to the אשם. asham פשיטא, Pshita, of course! הכי
אית ליה, Hachi it lei, that's exactly Rabbi Yehuda's position! What are
you telling us? No. הכא במאי עסקינן, we're talking about דנפק משמרתם
דהני ודהני, denafak mishmartam dehani udevani,
that group number one and group number two's weeks are over and
nobody brought the קרבן. korban Okay. ולא תבעו, Velo tavu,
and nobody demanded their rights from the other one. Group number one
never said give us the money, and when group number two was,
you know, it was their week, they never said to group number
one give us the אשם. asham So in that case, מהו דתימא
מחלי גבי הדדי, mahu deteima machali gabei hadadi, that everybody was sort
of מוחל mochel to everybody else, which basically means, I guess what
it would mean would be, group number two would keep their money
and then when it swung around again for group number one, they
would bring the אשם. asham And then the אשם would be coming
after the money. Understand? Because right the אשם was given to group
number one but it wasn't brought as a קרבן. korban The money
was given to group number two. So then assuming that like all,
you know, everybody is מוחל mochel everybody, you know, you keep yours,
we keep ours, then when it swings around 24 weeks from now
and group number one is מקריב it, the אשם is being brought
as a קרבן, korban being offered on the מזבח mizbe'ach after the
money was being given. Again, I don't understand why you're entitled to
do that. I would think you would just have to give the
קרבן korban to the next week and let them bring it. But
anyway, anyway קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, this teaches us that we don't
say that. דאמרינן, Deamrinan, כיון דלא תבעו להדדי קם ברישא. keivan delo
tavu lehadei kam bereisha.
Since no side made demands of the other side, it goes back
to the normal הלכה, halacha, which is that the money follows the
קרבן. korban So group number two gives the money to group number
one and I guess they wait 24 weeks to bring it. Again,
I don't know, because the there's a 24-week cycle of the משמרות.
mishmarot. So like I don't get it, you're allowed to hold on
to an animal that was given to your משמר to wait to
bring it? Or is it just that group number two gives the
money to group number one and the קרבן korban. is brought by
group number three? You know, I don't know, very strange. Yes. Do
they take a קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim outside once? Yeah,
before it's שחט, shachted, you can, yeah. Yeah. But are they bringing
all the animals? You're saying they're bringing all the animals with them
when they go back home? No, that would make no sense. Yeah,
exactly. But the whole idea that you can like wait and hold,
I don't get it exactly. Unless it's of the holidays where they're
like a משמר that's always there. Oh that's true, you could wait
till the רגל regel also and then bring it there maybe. I
don't know, very strange. Alright. When they switch משמרות, mishmarot, the משמר
is walking to Jerusalem from where they live. Right. So the מעמדות
mamadot are following them?
No, the מעמדות mamadot stay, the מעמדות mamadot stay. Now there are
Jews that are ישראל that stay in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash.
to represent the Jewish community. But the מעמדות mamadot are in are
in the individual cities. Not the כהנים didn't come from all over
the country. Many sort of stayed where they was. Right. I mean
you would have too many people working in the בית המקדש. Okay,
but they sort of, yeah, but they had their whole משמר system
in the cities as well. We're not going to deal with that.
Okay. מנהני מילי, Minani mili, that he brings the גזל gezel before
the he brings the אשם. You have to bring the גזל gezel
before the אשם and not the reverse. מנהני מילי, Minani mili, where
do you know this from? אמר רבא דבר קרא, Amar Rava devar
kra, האשם המושב לה' לכהן, Ha'asham hamushav la'Hashem lakohen, the אשם which
here says means the money that is returned to God goes to
the כהן, מלבד milvad
in addition to איל הכפורים אשר יכפר בו עליו, Eil hakippurim asher
yichaper bo alav, the ram of atonement that he will be atoned
for. So מכלל דכסף ברישא. Michlal dechesef bereisha. first it's the money
and then it mentions the ram of atonement the אשם. אמר ליה
מרבנן לרבא: Amar leh mi-rabbanan le-Rava:
so one of the rabbis said to רבא, אלא מעתה, ela me-ata,
מלבד עולת הבוקר אשר לעולת התמיד. milvad olat haboker asher le-olat hatamid.
If it says by the מוסף musaf that you bring the מוסף
musaf other in you know in addition to the morning עולה, ola,
so does that mean that the מוסף musaf comes first and then
the morning עולה? ola? הכי נמי מכלל דמוספין ברישא? hachi nami mikhlal
de-musafin be-reisha?
So should you read because it says in addition to that means
the second thing mentioned afterwards comes second? והתניא ותניא ברישא: ve-hatanya u-tanya
be-reisha: מנין שלא יהא דבר קודם לתמיד של שחר? mi-nayin she-lo yehei
davar kodem le-tamid shel shachar? How do you know nothing comes before
the morning sacrifice? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: וערך עליה העולה. ve-arach aleha
ha-ola.
You bring on it, you know, the עולה ola on the morning
sacrifice. The morning sacrifice is the thing that starts the day. So
just because it says מלבד milvad doesn't mean that that thing comes
next. ואמר רבא: ve-amar Rava: העולה עולה
ראשונה. ha-ola ola rishona. העולה ha-ola means the first עולה, ola, the
עולה ola of תמיד tamid that is always the first thing. אמר
ליה, Amar leh, he said back to him: אנא מאשר יכפר בו
נפקא לי, ana mi-asher yechaper bo nafka lei, ועדיין לא כיפר. ve-adayin
lo kiper. I'm not just saying because it says מלבד. milvad. מלבד
milvad doesn't mean the thing said next comes second. I'm talking about
the future tense: מלבד איל הכפרים אשר יכפר בו, milvad eil ha-kippurim
asher yechaper bo, in addition to the sacrifice which he will be
atoned by. So the sacrifice has yet to be brought, okay? So
therefore it means you first give the money in addition to the
sacrifice which will be brought to achieve atonement. So that means the
sacrifice comes after the money. All right. גזל הגר. gezel ha-ger So
then it says, okay, the חומש chomesh is not מעכב. me-akev. תנו
רבנן: מנין שאם הביא מעילתו ולא הביא אשמו? mi-nayin she-im heivi me'ilato
ve-lo heivi ashamo?
So here's a parallel case that if a person misappropriates הקדש hekdesh
they have to return the value and a חומש chomesh and they
have to bring a קרבן korban just like this case,
okay? And it's also an אשם. So how do you know if
somebody brings the מעילה, me'ila, meaning the principal, ולא הביא אשמו ve-lo
heivi ashamo and he does not bring the אשם, אשמו ולא הביא
מעילתו ashamo ve-lo heivi me'ilato or the קרבן without the money, שלא
יצא, she-lo yatza, he did not fulfill the obligation, he doesn't get
atonement? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: באיל האשם ונסלח לו. be-eil ha-asham ve-nislach
lo.
The ram of אשם and he be forgiven. And that's read as
the איל eil is the קרבן and the אשם here is read
as the money. So only with the קרבן and the money it's
forgiven. מנין שאם הביא אשמו עד שלא הביא מעילתו שלא יצא? mi-nayin
she-im heivi ashamo ad she-lo heivi me'ilato she-lo yatza? How do you
know though the money has to be first? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
this is by מעילה, me'ila, same as we said by גזל הגר:
gezel ha-ger באיל האשם, be-eil ha-asham, האשם בכבר. ha-asham bikhvar. The ram
of the אשם. What allows it to be the ram of the
אשם is that the, again, the אשם here means the money is
that the money preceded it. It's pretty funny. You could have said
the order of the words means the money comes next, even reading
the word אשם as the money. But no, what frames it as
a קרבן for the for the atonement is that the atonement money
preceded it. It's the grammar of it. סמיכות. smichut. I understand. I
understand. יכול כשם שאיל ואשם מעכבין כך חומש מעכב? yachol kesheim she-eil
ve-asham me-akvin kach chomesh me-akev?
Maybe the fifth is מעכב? me-akev? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: באיל האשם
ונסלח לו. be-eil ha-asham ve-nislach lo. איל ואשם מעכבין בהקדש ואין חומש
מעכב. eil ve-asham me-akvin be-hekdesh ve-ein chomesh me-akev. No,
it's only the איל eil and the אשם that are required, that
prevent one from being atoned, and not the fifth. וילמד הקדש מהדיוט
והדיוט מהקדש. ve-yilmed hekdesh me-hedyot ve-hedyot me-hekdesh.
And we'll learn הקדש hekdesh from הדיוט, hedyot, meaning הקדש hekdesh is
מעילה, me'ila, הדיוט hedyot is גזל הגר. gezel ha-ger, It's both קרבנות
korbanot that you're bringing, but the sin, whether the sin against הקדש
hekdesh as opposed to a sin against
a commoner. והדיוט מהקדש. ve-hedyot me-hekdesh. הקדש מהדיוט. hekdesh me-hedyot. What do
we learn to מעילה me'ila from the case of גזל הגר? מה
אשם דהתם קרן. mah asham de-hasam keren. How do we know the
word אשם in the פסוק pasuk by מעילה me'ila meant the principal?
Because it was clear by the גזל הגר. By the גזל הגר
it said האשם מלבד איל הכפרים. ha-asham milvad eil ha-kippurim.
It was clear that the word אשם didn't mean the קרבן because
it says you return the אשם in addition to the ram. Okay?
So it was very clear in the גזל הגר that the word
אשם did not mean קרבן. The word אשם meant the principal. So
the same way we see there that אשם meant principal, אף אשם
דהכא קרן. af asham de-hacha keren. Even by מעילה me'ila it's less
clear, but we're going to assert that the word אשם by מעילה
me'ila means
principal. והדיוט מהקדש. ve-hedyot me-hekdesh. And then we learn the גזל הגר
from the מעילה me'ila case. מה הקדש אין חומש מעכב. mah hekdesh
ein chomesh me-akev. The same way we learned באיל האשם ונסלח לו
be-eil ha-asham ve-nislach lo that the חומש chomesh is not necessary. I
mean it's required, it doesn't prevent one from being atoned. אף הדיוט
נמי אין חומש מעכב. af hedyot nami ein chomesh me-akev. Same by
גזל הגר, although there's an obligation of חומש, chomesh, it does not
prevent atonement. הדרן עלך הגוזל עצים. Hadran alach ha-gozel eitzim. So now
we are done with that and we have five minutes to begin
the next פרק. perek. Yes, you can say the last line means
essentially a קנס knas is not מעכב me-akev your כפרה. קנס knas
is not מעכב me-akev your כפרה. Correct. I mean in this case
at least. Okay. Last פרק perek returns us to classic בבא קמא
Bava Kamma issues. I mean yes it's yet with you about stealing
but then it was a lot about this special case of swearing
and the special קרבן and the אשם etc. This sort of evokes
more similar the beginning of the ninth פרק. perek. Remember the beginning
of the ninth פרק perek focused on שינוי, shinui, right? In a
way, you know the seventh פרק perek introduced all these ideas, שינוי,
shinui, שינוי רשות, shinui reshut, שינוי מעשה shinui ma'aseh etc. etcetera, and
the beginning of the ninth פרק Perek was a heavy emphasis on
שינוי מעשה, Shinuy Maaseh, changing, physically changing of the object. This פרק
Perek is going to focus us a little bit more on the
שינוי רשות Shinuy Reshus aspects, the changing of possession, and again, under
what circumstances a גזלן gazlan pays or not or gives back the
object or not. Let's take a look.
We'll get started. הגוזל ומאכיל את בניו: Hagozel Umachil es banav: somebody
steals, we're back to גזילה, gezeilah, okay, and he feeds his kids,
you know, it's why he stole, נעבעך, nebach, he couldn't put food
on the table, he went to the supermarket, he stole the food,
he fed it to his kids. והניח לפניהם: V'hiniach lifnehem: and now
we're going to read this or, he didn't eat it, and he
stole and the money was left over after he died. פטורי לשלם:
Pturi l'shalem: they don't have to reimburse. Now that's a big shocker,
if the principal is still physically around, the object that was stolen,
why is it that they would not have to give it back
to the original owner? Okay, it's one thing if it no longer
exists, okay,
but we'll see about them in the גמרא. ואם היה דבר שיש
בו אחריות חייבין לשלם: V'im haya davar sheyeish bo achrayus chayavin l'shalem:
if it is something that has liens on it, they have to
pay. What? It sounds like if he stole something that has liens
on it. Well, the only thing that has liens on it is
like land. How do you steal land? Maybe slaves. So I don't
get it, like, it's a very strange משנה. Mishnah Why do you
not have to pay back if it's around, and why do you
have to pay back if the thing has liens on it? So
we are going to see there's going to be two very different
reads of this משנה. mishna. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
אמר רב חסדא: Amar Rav Chisda: גזל ולא נתייאשו הבעלים: Gezel lo
nisyashu habialim: if somebody stole something and the owners have not given
up hope, ובא אחר ואכלו: u'va acher v'achalo: and then somebody, I
stole something from Joe here, and then Charlie came and I stole
like Joe's apple and then Charlie came and he ate it. So
רצה מזה גובה ורצה מזה גובה: ratza mizeh goveh v'ratza mizeh goveh:
Joe can collect from me, I'm a גזלן, gazlan and he can
collect from Charlie. Charlie's also a גזלן gazlan. or a מזיק. mazik.
Now the first thing I would want to know would be whether
Charlie knew that it was stolen or not, right? I mean, can
he be sued as a גזלן gazlan even though it is true
that he just ate something that wasn't his, he took something from
Joe, but if he had rights to assume it was mine, חזקה
מה שתחת יד אדם הוא שלו, chazaka mah shetachas yad adam hu
shelo, he's like... yeah, but
in a case where he ate it with my permission and he
honestly believed it was mine, it's hard, you know, one would imagine
that
he should be פטור. pater. Okay, that's not being explicated with רב
חסדא. Rav Chisda. Okay, so let's assume that Charlie was aware that
it was stolen, make it easy. So now Joe can collect either
from me or from Charlie, okay, I'm a גזלן gazlan and Charlie's
a גזלן. רצה מזה גובה ורצה מזה גובה. Ratza mizeh goveh v'ratza
mizeh goveh. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? כל כמה דלא נתייאשו הבעלים, Kol
kamma d'lo nisyashu habialim, as long as Joe hasn't given up hope
of getting it back,
ברשותיה דמריה קאי, b'reshusei d'marei kai, it's still under his control. So
when Charlie ate it, he was also stealing from Joe.
Okay, okay. תנן: Tnan: הגוזל ומאכיל את בניו והניח לפניהם פטורי לשלם.
Hagozel u'maachilo es banav v'hiniach lifnehem pturi l'shalem. Somebody steals and he
feeds his kids and then he dies, the kids are exempt. Why
are the kids exempt? They ate the food that belonged to this
other guy. Okay, so תיובתא דרב חסדא: tyufta d'Rav Chisda: this is
a contradiction to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. אמר
לך רב חסדא: Amar lach Rav Chisda: רב חסדא Rav Chisda will
say back to you, כי תניא היא לאחר יאוש: ki tanyah hi
l'achar yeiush: no, the משנה mishna. is talking about לאחר יאוש. l'achar
yeiush. Now
why does לאחר יאוש l'achar yeiush matter? So you could say it's
an idea of a שינוי רשות. Shinuy reshus. ראובן Reuven steals and
he gives it to his kids and they eat it, so that's
a יאוש yeiush and now the kids are a separate רשות, reshus,
it's like it changed hands and now the kids own it, and
therefore that's why it's different. Okay, this is going to be the
question that we're going to get into in a minute, whether רשות
יורש כרשות לוקח דמי. reshus yoresh k'reshus lokaich dami. When somebody gives
it to his kids, okay, he bequeaths it to his kids, he
dies, or he actually gives it to his kids, you know, while
he's alive, he puts it on the table, are they seen as
a separate domain? Do they take possession? Would you say יאוש yeiush
and שינוי רשות Shinuy reshus if somebody gave it to his kids?
So תוספות says: we're going to get to that in a minute,
but I just want to lay out that תוספות says within this
read of the משנה mishna. you don't have to assert that. All
you have to assert is that once Joe's control of the object
has weakened because it's לאחר יאוש, l'achar yeiush, right? You remember from
all the stuff we've learned earlier, already once it's stolen from him,
his control over it is weakened, he can't sell it, the גזלן
can't sell it, neither have full ownership or control. Now not only
is it not out of his physical control, he's given up hope
of getting it back, okay, to the point that if a really
third party would come and take it, they'd be able to keep
it. So if a third party could take it and keep it,
then even if the kids are not considered a third party, but
Joe can't collect from them for being a מזיק mazik or for
being a גזלן since the object is basically waiting for somebody to
come and take it. I'll give you an example. Let's say you
had a lost object on the street and you were מייאש meyayesh
getting it back and I could pick it up and take it,
but rather than picking up and taking it, I stomped on it
and I broke it. Can you collect from me? You're a מזיק.
mazik. At that moment it was still mine, you hadn't taken possession
of it. The answer would be no. At that state where your
ownership is so weak, how can you collect from me? So what
רב חסדא Rav Chisda is saying is that our משנה is לאחר
יאוש. l'achar yeiush. לאחר יאוש L'achar yeiush the kids eat it, they
You can't collect from the kids. But that's also why and he...
Okay, so that's how he reads the משנה. How
we... we're going now read the rest of the משנה. We'll have
to wait for tomorrow. So דב, Dov, I'm giving you a little
bit of a challenge to take over. I'm not going to be
here tomorrow, but it is going to be a little bit tricky.
Two different ways of reading this משנה. We will continue with this
tomorrow. יישר כוח. Yasher koach.